Hi. This is Matt Baker. Today I’m going
to give you my answer to the question:
What is the oldest European country? I say “my
answer” because, when it comes to this question,
the answer is not as clear cut as you might think.
For example, do we count microstates such as San
Marino or only regular sized ones like Italy?
Do we use the United Kingdom or do we consider
England, Scotland, and Wales separately? What
about countries that ceased to exist for some
time, only to re-appear later, such as Po.
land? Do we count from their original founding
date (966) or from their modern one (1918)?
As you can see, it's all very complicated.
So, first of all, I want to make the point that
there were no European countries in ancient
times. Sure, there were some very important
civilizations, such as the Greeks and Romans
but in ancient times, they existed either in the
form of individual city-states or as empires.
Countries (which are usually larger than a
city but smaller than an empire) came later,
sometime after the fall of Rome. They are
more regional in nature and in most cases,
trace their origin to the Middle Ages, when some
local warlord united a bunch of nearby tribes,
usually based on a shared language and culture.
It is for this reason that I chose to start
my Timeline of European History chart around
the year 800 CE. Sure, there was obviously a
lot of history that occurred in Europe before
this point but an argument could be made
that that was more Mediterranean history,
than European history, meaning that the center
of action was based around the Mediterranean
Sea rather than on the continent of Europe as a
whole. You see, it wasn’t until the Middle Ages
that the continent itself became the stage for
events because that’s when a bunch of countries
suddenly formed and started interacting with
each other as independent, regional entities.
So, when it comes to figuring out which European
country is the oldest, I’m only going to be strict
about two things. First, I’m not going include
any microstates. To me, they are anomalies that
don’t follow the usual pattern so I’m going
to focus on country-sized countries only. So,
say goodbye to Andorra, Liechtenstein, Malta,
Monaco, San Marino, and Vatican City. Second,
when it comes to the transcontinental countries
(meaning those that can be considered both
European and Asian), I am going to include Russia
but I’m not going to include any of the others,
such as Armenia, Azerbaijan, Cyprus, Georgia,
Kazakhstan, or Turkey (because, historically,
these countries are more closely linked to West
Asia than to Europe). However, when it comes to
everything else, I’m going to be super lenient.
So, rather than focus on when each country got
its current name, or achieved its modern borders
or in some cases, regained its independence, I’m
instead just going to focus on when each country
first emerged as a unique self-governing entity.
Now, to make things easy, I’m next going
to remove any remaining countries that were
formed in modern times (meaning those that were
never a unified, independent state during the
Middle Ages; those two words: unified and
independent being key factors). Obviously,
none of them are going to be among
the oldest—so this removes Austria,
Belgium, Estonia, Finland, Greece, Ireland,
Italy, Latvia, Luxembourg, Netherlands,
North Macedonia, Slovakia, and Slovenia. Which
means that we now have only 24 countries left
(actually, 25, because I’m going to
consider England & Scotland separately)
So, let's now go through each one, using this
Timeline of European History chart. We’ll start
with the three main Scandinavian countries:
Denmark, Norway, and Sweden. As you can see,
Norway was controlled by Sweden for most of
the 19th century and before that, by Denmark
for around 300 years; and then before that: all
three were united as the Kalmar Union. However,
during most of the Middle Ages, they were three
separate kingdoms. And, if we keep going up,
we discover that Norway is actually the oldest of
three, having been founded by Harald Fairhair in
872. Denmark came next, in 936, and then Sweden in
970. Now, I do realize that these are traditional
dates based on semi-legendary sources but
like I said, I’m going to be quite lenient
(I’ll only come back to the issue of historicity
if we need to break a tie). Now, before we move on
from the Nordic countries, I want to add Iceland.
Down here, I show that it became a part of Norway
in the 13th century. However, before this, it
actually existed as an independent commonwealth,
starting from the year 930. So let’s
add Iceland to the list, above Denmark.
Next up, let’s look at England and Scotland. They
merged to become Great Britain in 1707 (which is
today called the United Kingdom) but before
this, had very long histories of their own.
As we move back up, I also want to address Wales
as we pass it. Like Ireland, Wales never really
existed as a single, unified kingdom during
medieval times. The closest it came was when
Llweylyn the Great established the Principality
of Wales but it was quickly absorbed into England.
If we keep going up, we see that England was ruled
by Denmark for awhile but was founded in 886 by
Alfred the Great (although it was actually his
grandson Aethelstan who first used the term “King
of the English”). Scotland is a little bit older,
having been founded by Kenneth MacAlpin in 843.
Now, next, I want to move back down and
talk a bit about Spain. Like Great Britain,
Spain was actually formed by the merger of two
previously independent kingdoms, in this case:
Castile and Aragon in 1479. Castile is
generally seen as being the dominant one,
so, since I’m being lenient, I’m not
going to use 1479 for Spain but instead,
I’m going to continue to trace Castile
back a little further. As you can see,
it too was actually formed by a merger between
two kingdoms, this time: Castile and Leon. And,
if we keep going back, we see that, once upon a
time Spain actually consisted of four kingdoms:
Castille, Leon, Aragon, and Navarre (with the
ruler of the largest one often using the title
“Emperor of All Spain”. So, I know it’s debatable,
but I’m going to use 1065 as the start date for
Spain because that’s when there was, for the
first time ever, four Spanish kingdoms. Take
note that Portugal actually formed a bit later,
in 1139, when it split off from Castile & Leon.
Okay, we now come to a really big one: France.
If we follow the blue line up we see that it
was originally known as the Kingdom of the
West Franks and that, at the very top, West
Francia connects the Empire of Charlemagne. Now,
also connecting to Charlemagne is East Francia,
which corresponds to Germany. It eventually
became the Holy Roman Empire but take note
that the core part of the Holy Roman Empire was
always what historians refer to as the medieval
Kingdom of Germany. So, although Germany is
usually said to have been founded in 1871,
I think it’s fair to say that
Germany is actually much, much older.
Now, going back up to the top, I want to make the
point that, originally, France and Germany were
a single country: Francia. And Francia actually
goes back much farther than Charlemagne. In fact,
it goes all the way back to 481 (which is
just 5 years after the fall of Rome). So,
I’ve got a choice here. Do I use the year 481 for
both France and Germany or do I use the year 843,
which is when the Treaty of Verdun split the
Franks into three pieces (with only two pieces
surviving: West and East, which became France
and Germany). Well, I’m going to go with 843
because that’s when each side started to develop
their own unique histories. Now, as you can see,
this puts France and Germany into a three-way
tie with Scotland so, like I mentioned earlier,
I think we need to bring up the issue of
historicity here. When it comes to Scotland,
there is some debate over whether 843 actually
marks the point in which Scotland became truly
united. Some argue that the reign of Constantine
II, starting in 900, would be more accurate.
In contrast, 843 is a very solid date for
when Charlemagne’s Empire was split. Thus,
while I’m going to keep Scotland at 843, I’m
going to put France and Germany above it.
Okay, next up, I want to address Hungary. As you
can see, Hungary was founded in the year 1000.
Eventually, it was inherited by the Habsburgs
(who were from Austria and had become Holy
Roman Emperors). But because they held Austria
and Hungary separately from the imperial title,
when the Holy Roman Empire fell apart, they
continued to rule both Austria and Hungary (with
Germany going in a totally different direction
at this point). Now, another part of the Holy
Roman Empire that eventually developed
its own unique history is Switzerland.
It actually traces its roots all the way back to
1291 so that’s the date I’m going to use for it.
We now come to the Slavic countries. The only two
West Slavic countries that go back to medieval
times are Czechia and Poland. For most of
its history, Czechia was known as Bohemia,
and while it was held in personal
union with Hungary for a long time,
and before that was a part of the Holy Roman
Empire, it actually has independent roots that
go all the way back to 870. Poland was founded
a bit later, in 966. It later went through a
period of fragmentation only to re-emerge
during the 14th century, eventually forming
a union with Lithuania. Lithuania was founded
in 1253 so let’s add that to the list as well.
Now, when it comes to East Slavic
countries, there are three: Russia,
Belarus, and Ukraine. They all trace their origin
back to Kyivan Rus, which was founded in 882. So,
should I give 882 to all three countries?
Well, since I went with when Francia split
for the start dates for both France and Germany,
I think I should go with when Kyivan Rus split
for the start dates for Russia, Belarus, and
Ukraine. This occurred around the year 1200.
Galicia-Volhynia roughly corresponds to Ukraine
and while it was eventually conquered by Poland
and then later Russia, the region did develop
its own unique language and culture. Likewise,
it was the Grand-Principality of Vladimir, which
eventually evolved into Moscow, which eventually
evolved into Russia. And, while it’s not shown
on the chart, there also existed a medieval
principality called Polotsk, which followed
a different trajectory and is today Belurus.
In terms of South Slavic countries,
the oldest is Croatia, founded in 925.
It entered into a personal union with Hungary,
around the same time that Serbia emerged as an
independent entity (which was in 1091).
It’s not on the chart but there was also
an independent state called Duklja around this
time (starting from 1077) which corresponds to
modern day Montenegro. Finally, came
Bosnia, which formally split from
Hungary in 1377. During that same century, two
non-slavic countries also split from Hungary:
Wallachia in 1330 (which eventually became a
core part of Romania) and Moldova in 1359. Oh,
and I should also point out Arbanon, which emerged
in 1190 and is the earliest Albanian state.
Alright, we now have only 1 country
left: Bulgaria. And it’s good that
this one came last because, although it’s
shown on this chart as beginning in 864,
it actually goes back (as an independent
entity) all the way to 681. Which means that,
according my criteria, Bulgaria
is the oldest European country;
followed by France and Germany (tied at 2),
Scotland at 4, and Czechia (formerly known as
Bohemia) at 5. Rounding out the top 10 would be
Norway, England, Croatia, Iceland, and Denmark.
Now, like I said, there are multiple ways to
answer the question and I’m sure many of you
have strong opinions about my choices. So let me
give you some alternative answers. Bulgaria was
ruled by the Byzantines and Ottomans for much
of its history, so if you want to go with the
oldest continuously-existing independent European
country, that would be France (because there was
a space in-between the Holy Roman Empire and
the German Empire when Germany was not united).
However, if you want to include microstates,
the oldest European country would be San Marino,
which was founded in 301 CE. But, if you also
wanted to include the transcontinental countries,
well then you’re looking at Armenia (which was
founded all the way back in 331 BCE). Finally,
if you want to throw out all of the rules and
just go with the country where the earliest
European civilization was established, well
that would probably be Greece because the
Minoan civilization on the island of
Crete goes back to around 3000 BCE.
So, yeah, like I said at the beginning, there
are lots of ways to answer the question. My
preference is to go with either Bulgaria (if
you’re okay with periods of foreign rule)
or France (if you’re not). Let me know in the
comments what your opinion is. And, of course,
if you want to get a copy of the chart as a
poster, just head over to UsefulCharts.com
or just use the link in the description
or pinned comment. I’ll also leave a link
on screen to a video we did previously that
goes through the chart in even greater detail.
Until next time, thanks for watching.